<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>jQuery Text Alignment Plugin</title>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Download</title>

    <para>Version 0.02 ― 2009-07-02.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jquery.text-align.js">jquery.text-align.js</ulink>
        (Uncompressed, 1.5KB)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="jquery.text-align.min.js">jquery.text-align.min.js</ulink>
        (Minified, 0.8KB)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Example</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="examples.html">Text alignment example</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>This plugin is licensed under the <ulink type=""
    url="/licenses/BSD.txt">new BSD license</ulink>. To summarize the license;
    the plugin is completely free for commercial and non-commercial use and
    you can do with it whatever you want, except claim it as your own
    work.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Imagine you have worked hard to make your tables look good, but one
    thing keeps bugging you; the alignment of the text in the cells. You
    would, for example, like to align the contents of each cell on the comma
    character. Unfortunately, no browser supports aligning table cells on
    characters. This is where the jQuery Text Alignment Plugin comes in; it
    adds support for aligning text based on characters to all browsers.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Please keep in mind that when this plugin is used to align on
      characters, it will convert the children of the element it is called on
      to text, and apply the alignment to that. Inline markup will thus be
      effectively removed. Future versions of this plugin might correct this,
      once I figure out what to do with complex content.</para>
    </note>

    <para>The following examples selects all the cells in an example table,
    then uses the <ulink url="../column/">jQuery Column Selector
    plugin</ulink> to select the first column, and finally aligns the cells in
    that column on the comma character.</para>

    <programlisting>$('#example td:nth-col(1)').textAlign(',');</programlisting>

    <para>The <methodname>textAlign</methodname> method only accepts a single
    parameter, and will align all selected elements according to the same
    criteria. The method returns the elements it was called on, and can thus
    be chained.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>textAlign(str)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Aligns the text in the selected elements according to
          <parameter>str</parameter> parameter. The parameter can either be
          one of the following keywords, or a single character:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>left</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements to the left.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>right</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements to the right.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>center</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements centered.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>justify</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements justified.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>start</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements according to the left-to-right locale
                (start means left in western languages.)</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>end</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the elements according to the left-to-right locale
                (end means right in western languages.)</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>&lt;character&gt;</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Align the the elements on the character. Note that
                elements that do not have the character are aligned as if they
                ended with the character. The element as a whole is aligned
                according to the inherited text alignment property,</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Please see the <ulink url="examples.html">text alignment example
    page</ulink> for example code on how to use the plugin.</para>
  </section>
</article>