<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Latest updates</title>

  <sidebar>
    <title>About</title>

    <para>I'm a programmer and web developer from the Netherlands with a
    passion for creating usable software, websites, and when I have some spare
    time, games.</para>

    <para>This site contains some of my work and hobby projects. Feel free to
    look around.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Feed</title>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="/images/feed.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject> <ulink url="rss.xml">RSS Feed</ulink></para>
  </sidebar>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/column/">jQuery
    column selector plugin</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Thursday 16 April 2009</subtitle>

    <para>New project time; I mentioned some time ago that I was close to
    finishing two new projects. Today I finally got around to releasing a new
    <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/column/">jQuery plugin for
    selecting table columns</ulink>. The plugin adds a new selector to the
    jQuery selector API for retrieving table cells by their column index. It
    supports tables with column and row spans transparently, no matter how
    complex a table is. The syntax for selecting column cells is simple and
    similar to other jQuery selectors, so the learning curve should be very
    small.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout
    updated &amp; jQuery UI integration example</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Wednesday 15 April 2009</subtitle>

    <para>The <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout
    library</ulink> has received an update; the new version is mostly a
    refactoring of the code and as a result the file size is slightly smaller
    than before (while keeping the same functionality.) It is also a first
    step towards integration with the jQuery UI framework. Also included in
    this update is a new example which demonstrates how to use the jQuery UI
    framework to make a <ulink type=""
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/borderlayout-resize.html">full-screen
    resizable border layout</ulink>. As a bonus, this version has been tested
    with jQuery 1.3.2, which works just fine.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink type=""
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/object-oriented-javascript.html">Book
    Review: Object Oriented JavaScript</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Tuesday 31 March 2009</subtitle>

    <para>A few weeks ago I was asked by <ulink type=""
    url="http://www.packtpub.com/">Packt Publishing</ulink> to review one of
    their titles “<ulink
    url="http://www.packtpub.com/object-oriented-javascript-applications-libraries/book">Object
    Oriented JavaScript: Create scalable, reusable high-quality JavaScript
    applications and libraries</ulink>” by Stoyan Stefanov. As an avid reader
    and obsessed with all things JavaScript I couldn't say no, as you can see
    in <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/object-oriented-javascript.html">my
    review of Object Oriented JavaScript</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/xsltjson/">New
    XSLTJSON version</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Friday 27 February 2009</subtitle>

    <para>I've just uploaded a <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/xsltjson/">new XSLTJSON
    version</ulink>, with exactly one new feature and two minor bug fixes. It
    is now possible to skip the root element of a XML document and only have
    the child elements returned using the skip-root parameter. The
    <acronym>JSONP</acronym> support has changed to not produce parentheses
    when it is turned off (invalidating the <acronym>JSON</acronym>), and the
    stylesheet now supports <acronym>XML</acronym> parsers that do not
    properly match entity encoded new line control characters (that's a
    mouthful, but what it comes down to is that running XSLTJSON on some XSLT
    processors generated JSON with unescaped newlines.)</para>

    <para>Last updated I mentioned two new projects that have kept me busy. I
    haven't finished either project yet, but I'll give some hints as to the
    nature of one of them: <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/chart/scatter.png">Canvas</ulink>,
    <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/chart/bar.png">JavaScript</ulink>,
    <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/chart/line.png">chart</ulink>,
    <ulink type=""
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/chart/plot.png">plotting</ulink>,
    and <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/chart/histogram.png"
    userlevel="">almost finished</ulink>. I hope you can figure it out from
    that.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jQuery 1.3
    support for jLayout</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Saturday 17 January 2009</subtitle>

    <para>Happy belated new year! It has been a while since I posted; moving
    twice, starting a new job, and writing your thesis simultaneously tends to
    do that. Things seem to be calming down now, and I hope to finish and
    release two new projects soon. In the meantime I've set up a <ulink
    type="" url="http://groups.google.com/group/jlayout/">support group for
    the jLayout library</ulink> for general discussion and support. I have
    also tested both <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout</ulink> and
    <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jsizes/">JSizes</ulink> with
    the new <ulink
    url="http://blog.jquery.com/2009/01/14/jquery-13-and-the-jquery-foundation/">jQuery
    1.3 release</ulink>. Neither required any changes, so no new release. I
    did however remove the “experimental” warning on the jLayout plugin page,
    and consider it stable and reasonably well tested―it works in all major
    browsers including Internet Explorer 6.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jfun/">Functional
    Pattern Matching in JavaScript</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Sunday 05 October 2008</subtitle>

    <para>I've turned the articles on pattern matching in JavaScript into a
    library. The code is completely rewritten, shorter, more efficient, better
    tested and no longer depends on the Junify unification library. Please see
    the <ulink type="" url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jfun/">project
    page</ulink> for details on the syntax, documentation and examples.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">New jLayout
    algorithm &amp; IE6 support</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Saturday 04 October 2008</subtitle>

    <para>I've uploaded a new version of <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout</ulink>, with
    support for a new layout algorithm called ‘flex-grid’. The flex-grid
    algorithm allows you to lay out components in a grid with flexible column
    and row sizes. The <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/jquery-plugin.html">jLayout
    jQuery plugin</ulink> has also been updated and now supports Internet
    Explorer 6 (in standards mode). Support for IE6 brought up a small bug in
    the <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jsizes/">JSizes jQuery
    plugin</ulink>, which has now been corrected as well.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink type=""
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/xsltjson/">Rayfish convention
    support for XSLTJSON</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Wednesday 03 September 2008</subtitle>

    <para>The XSLTJSON project now supports <ulink
    url="http://onperl.org/blog/onperl/page/rayfish">Micheal Matthew's Rayfish
    convention</ulink> for converting XML to JSON. The Rayfish convention
    creates highly structured JSON from your XML, and is a good choice when
    dealing with data centric XML files. Additionally I've created unit tests
    for all supported output formats and made sure that all are
    passing.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JavaScript Pattern Matching &amp; JUnify, jLayout updates</title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Tuesday 12 August 2008</subtitle>

    <para>I've uploaded a new article on <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/advanced-pattern-matching.html">advanced
    functional pattern matching in JavaScript</ulink>. The article introduces
    a simplified pattern matching syntax, and shows how to use it with
    algebraic data types. There are also new versions of the <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/junify/">JUnify library</ulink> and
    the <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout
    library</ulink>. The new JUnify version contains a small modification to
    work together with <ulink
    url="http://w3future.com/weblog/stories/2008/06/16/adtinjs.xml">Sjoerd
    Visscher's algebraic data type library</ulink>, and the jLayout library
    now includes support for Safari 3.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout
    Layout Algorithms &amp; jQuery plugin</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Monday 4 August 2008</subtitle>

    <para>The <ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/">jLayout
    JavaScript library</ulink> provides layout algorithms for laying out
    components and containers. The library currently provides two layout
    algorithms: border, which lays out components in five different regions
    and grid, which lays out components in a user defined grid. An <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jlayout/jquery-plugin.html"
    userlevel="">experimental jQuery plugin</ulink> to lay out (X)HTML
    elements is also available.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/junify/">JUnify
    unification library</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Friday 1 August 2008</subtitle>

    <para>JUnify is a JavaScript library for performing unification on objects
    and arrays. Unification is an algorithm to determine the substitutions
    needed to make two expressions match. If the expressions contain
    variables, these will be bound to values in order for the match to
    succeed. If two expressions are not identical or the variables can not be
    bound, the match fails. Unification can, for example, be used to implement
    <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/pattern-matching.html">pattern
    matching</ulink>, <ulink
    url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/extracting-object-values.html">object
    property extraction</ulink>, or an expert system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><ulink url="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/jsizes/">JSizes
    jQuery plugin</ulink></title>

    <subtitle>Posted on Saturday 26 July 2008</subtitle>

    <para>JSizes is a small plugin for the jQuery JavaScript library which
    adds support for the CSS min-width, min-height, max-width, max-height,
    border-*-width, margin, and padding properties. Additionally it has one
    method for determining whether an element is visible. Because all the size
    methods return numbers, it is safe to use them in calculating DOM element
    dimensions.</para>
  </section>
</article>