<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>jQuery column cell selector</title>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Download</title>

    <para>Version 0.12 ― 2009-04-16.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink type="" url="jquery.column.js">jquery.column.js</ulink>
        (Uncompressed, 2.4KB)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jquery.column.min.js">jquery.column.min.js</ulink>
        (Minified, 1.3KB)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>This plugin requires at least version 1.3 of jQuery.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>This plugin is licensed under the <ulink type=""
    url="/licenses/BSD.txt">new BSD license</ulink>. To summarize the license;
    it is completely free for commercial and non-commercial use and you can do
    with it whatever you want, except claim it as your own work.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This plugin adds a new selector to the jQuery selector API for
    retrieving table cells by their column index. It supports tables with
    column and row spans transparently, no matter how complex your table is.
    The syntax is simple and similar to other jQuery selectors so there is a
    very small learning curve. The following example shows how to select all
    the cells in the fourth column of a table.</para>

    <programlisting>$('#mytable tbody td:nth-col(4)');</programlisting>

    <para>The selector can take several types of arguments for selecting
    columns, such as keywords, numeric indexes, and equations. These are
    explained in more detail in the API section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>API</title>

    <para>This plugin adds one new pseudo selector to the jQuery selector API,
    called <methodname>nth-col</methodname>. Additionally it adds one new
    method to the jQuery function namespace called
    <methodname>nthCol</methodname> (which one to use depends on your use
    case, please refer to the <acronym>FAQ</acronym> section for details.)
    Both the selector and extension function provide the same functionality
    and accept the same arguments. The following arguments can be used:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>even</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Selects and returns all cells in even columns.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>odd</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Selects and returns all cells in uneven columns.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>equation</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>An equation in the form of <code>a * n + b</code>, where both
          <varname>a</varname> and <varname>b</varname> can be negative or
          positive, and n represents the column index. This will split the
          columns in groups of size <varname>a</varname> and select the child
          with position <varname>b</varname> in each group. Both
          <varname>a</varname> and <varname>b</varname> are optional, but at
          least one should be provided. The syntax is identical to that of the
          <ulink
          url="http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-css3-selectors-20090310/#nth-child-pseudo">CSS
          nth-child pseudo selector</ulink>. Invalid equations are ignored and
          return no results.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>number</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Selects and returns a single column with the specified numeric
          index. This is a simplified version of the equation syntax.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Note that column numbering starts at one, not at zero as in most
    programming languages. Please have a look at the examples in the next
    section to see how the equation syntax is used.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>The following are all examples of using both the column selector and
    extension function. Note that the syntax for both is identical, but that
    equations and keywords passed to the <methodname>nthCol</methodname>
    extension function must be properly escaped.</para>

    <programlisting>// select all even cells in the tbody section of #mytable
$('#mytable tbody td:nth-col(even)');

// same as above, but using the nthCol extension function
$('#mytable tbody td').nthCol('even');

// selects both table header and table data cells from the third column of #mytable
$('#mytable th:nth-col(3), #mytable td:nth-col(3)');

// same as above but using the nthCol extension function
$('#mytable th, #mytable td).nthCol(3);

// select the first element in the third group
$('#mytable td:nth-col(3n+1)');

// same as above but using the nthCol extension function
$('#mytable td').nthCol('3n+1');

// select the cells in the 9th, 19th, 29th, etc, column of #mytable
$('#mytable td:nth-col(10n-1)');</programlisting>

    <para>More examples are available on a separate page which shows <ulink
    url="examples.html">examples of column selectors</ulink> used with tables
    containing complicated column and row spans.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>What is the difference between the selector and the nthCol
        jQuery extension function?</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Although both use the same code, the
          <methodname>nthCol</methodname> extension function is probably
          faster. The reason for this is that the selector engine in jQuery
          uses a bottom up approach. This is a good thing for most selectors,
          but not so much for a column selector because it needs context
          information, such as access to rows and table sections
          (<code>thead</code>, <code>tbody</code> and <code>tfoot</code>.) For
          example, say you write the following selector: "<code>#mytable tbody
          td:nth-col(even)</code>". The selector engine will first select all
          <code>td</code> elements in your document and pass them to the
          column selector. This means the column selector will have to
          calculate the correct column cells for all tables in the document
          instead of just the ones in <code>#mytable</code>. Although it does
          so in the most efficient way possible, there is still a cost for
          doing these calculations on tables you did not intend to select. The
          <methodname>nthCol</methodname> extension function on the other hand
          works on the result of the selector, meaning all irrelevant elements
          have already been thrown out, and as such it does not do any
          unnecessary work. My recommendation for now is that you start with
          using the column selector in your code, and only if profiling shows
          a performance problem switch to the <code>nthCol</code> extension
          function.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Why not just use col and colgroup?</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>There are several reasons you might want to use this plugin
          over <classname>col</classname> and <classname>colgroup</classname>.
          First, <ulink
          url="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/tables.html#columns"><classname>col</classname>
          and <classname>colgroup</classname> are restricted in the CSS
          attributes they support</ulink>, which may be problematic if you
          want to do advanced styling. They are limited because
          <classname>col</classname> and <classname>colgroup</classname>
          define artificial elements that are not actually there in the source
          document. This plugin on the other hand returns the actual table
          cells that make up the column. These cells can then be styled in any
          way. Second, browser support for those <classname>col</classname>
          and <classname>colgroup</classname> attributes that can be styled is
          <ulink
          url="http://www.quirksmode.org/css/columns.html">problematic</ulink>,
          while all browsers fully support styling table cells.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>What is the difference between using this plugin and using the
        standard "#mytable tbody &gt; td:nth-child(n)" selector?</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>For tables that have no row or column span attributes this
          works just fine, and is the recommended method if you know for sure
          your tables will never contain a row or column span. If you have row
          or column spans in your table, or at least the possibility that they
          might one day be there, you should use the column selector plugin
          which handles column and row spans correctly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <para>The algorithm used in the column selector was inspired by the work
    done by <ulink type="" url="http://www.javascripttoolbox.com/">Matt Kruse
    of The Javascript Toolbox</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
</article>