<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>OpenGL GUI library for games</title>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Download</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Library source: <ulink url="UI.zip">UI.zip</ulink> (7,084 KB -
        All platforms)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X Framework: <ulink
        url="UI.framework.zip">UI.framework.zip</ulink> (541 KB - Mac OS X
        Universal Binary)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Demo applications: <ulink
        url="examples.zip">examples.zip</ulink> (966 KB - Windows only)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>The GUI library is released under the <ulink
    url="/licenses/BSD.txt">revised BSD license</ulink>. This means it is
    compatible with the GNU GPL license. The complete license can be found in
    the source code.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <note>
    <para>The library is no longer maintained due to a lack of time. The
    downloads and articles are still available for reference. Feel free to
    fork or otherwise use the source code and articles (please let me know if
    you do so, I would love to know where it ends up.)</para>
  </note>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><emphasis>This is a Graphical User Interface (GUI) library for
    prototyping and building game user interfaces.</emphasis><emphasis> It is
    based on </emphasis><ulink
    url="http://www.opengl.org/">OpenGL</ulink><emphasis> and written in
    (portable) C++. The library is completely free and open-source. Other
    features include:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>widgets such as buttons, scrollbars, menuitems, textfields,
        etc.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ability to modify and create custom themes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>can be used as an in-game texture (see UITest in the
        demo's)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API similar to Java Swing API</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BSD license on source code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Latest news</title>

    <section>
      <title>Mac OS X update</title>

      <subtitle>2006-07-18</subtitle>

      <para>There were some small problems with the .framework OS X release.
      Thanks to Jeffrey Wilcke these have now been fixed. As a bonus, I have
      also tested the library under <ulink
      url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/vstudio/express/visualC/default.aspx">Microsoft
      Visual C++ 2005 Express</ulink> (free and highly recommended) and fixed
      some other small things. The new release can be found in the download
      sidebar.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mac OS X port and maintenance release</title>

      <subtitle>2006-07-02</subtitle>

      <para>I've uploaded a new version of the library, which includes a port
      to Mac OS X. The source distribution includes a XCode project file as
      well as several bug fixes and a new theme. This new theme, although
      unfinished at this time, should make it easier to write custom themes.
      There is also a precompiled Mac OS X .framework distribution. The demo
      applications have not yet been ported, so they only work in Windows (for
      now).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Articles and documentation</title>

    <para>Here are some articles, notes and documentation on the GUI
    library.</para>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="#">API</ulink></title>

      <para>API documentation generated from the source code. Updated with
      each new release.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/gettingstarted.html">Getting
      started</ulink></title>

      <para>This article describes everything from downloading and installing
      to creating your first OpenGL GUI. In short; everything you need to get
      started.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/fontengine.html">Writing a font
      engine</ulink></title>

      <para>Because the library does not come with a standard font engine,
      this article will explain to you how to write your own font engine for
      use with the library.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/selection.html">How selection
      works</ulink></title>

      <para>This article will describe how the selection of Components works.
      There are several ways of accomplishing the selection of items on a
      computer screen and in this article, three such methods are discussed
      and compared for their suitability within the library. This article
      assumes you have some understanding of how the Component hierarchy works
      and some basic OpenGL knowledge.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/codeconventions.html">Code
      conventions</ulink></title>

      <para>This document describes the programming style I used while writing
      the library. I did not write it to talk you or anyone else into using it
      (although that would be nice.) It could come in handy if you're
      interested in writing your own Components and contributing to the
      project, although you're of course free to use whatever coding
      convention you see fit. In the end, I don't really care what you use, as
      long as you use it consistently.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/memorynote.html">A note on memory
      management</ulink></title>

      <para>This note describes the memory ownership policy used in the
      library, and why this particular ownership policy was chosen.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><ulink url="../../articles/openglcanvas.html">Creating an OpenGL
      component</ulink></title>

      <para>A step by step tutorial of how to create an OpenGL component
      inside the GUI.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Screenshots</title>

    <para><ulink url="gui.png">Click here to enlarge</ulink></para>

    <graphic fileref="gui_thumb.png" />
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Not what you're looking for?</title>

    <para>That happens. Here are some alternative OpenGL GUI libraries (in no
    particular order):</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://glgooey.sourceforge.net/">http://glgooey.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        - GLGooey</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://turska.sourceforge.net/">http://turska.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        - Turska</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://glam.sourceforge.net/">http://glam.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        - GLAM</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://glui.sourceforge.net/">http://glui.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        - GLUI</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://libufo.sourceforge.net/">http://libufo.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        - LibUFO</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.cegui.org.uk/">http://www.cegui.org.uk/</ulink> -
        Crazy Eddie's GUI system</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <para>Thanks to: Jeffrey Wilcke (Mac OS X help).</para>
  </section>
</article>