<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Articles on programming</title>

  <section>
    <title>JavaScript</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="extracting-object-values.html">Extracting values
        from JavaScript objects</ulink></para>

        <para>A simple tutorial on using the <ulink
        url="../projects/junify/">JUnify unification library</ulink> to
        implement a simple object property extractor. The end result allows
        you to extract properties from objects in a style similar to
        destructuring assignment in JavaScript 1.7.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="pattern-matching.html">Pattern matching in
        JavaScript</ulink></para>

        <para>A step by step guide for implementing conditional pattern
        matching as seen in functional programming languages such as ML,
        Erlang and Haskell. The guide makes heavy use of the <ulink
        url="../projects/junify/">JUnify library</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="advanced-pattern-matching.html">Advanced pattern
        matching in JavaScript</ulink></para>

        <para>A continuation of the pattern matching article. This article
        introduces a simplified pattern syntax, an optimization and explains
        how to use pattern matching together with algebraic data types.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Book Reviews</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>“<ulink
        url="http://www.bramstein.com/articles/object-oriented-javascript.html">Object
        Oriented JavaScript: Create scalable, reusable high-quality JavaScript
        applications and libraries</ulink>” by Stoyan Stefanov</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Graphical User Interface Library</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="gettingstarted.html">Getting started</ulink></para>

        <para>This article describes everything from downloading and
        installing the library to creating your first OpenGL GUI. In short;
        everything you need to know to create a basic user interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="fontengine.html">Writing a font
        engine</ulink></para>

        <para>This article will explain to you how to write your own font
        engine for use with the GUI library.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="selection.html">How selection works</ulink></para>

        <para>This article will describe how the selection of Components
        works. There are several ways of accomplishing the selection of items
        on a computer screen and in this article, three such methods are
        discussed and compared for their suitability within the
        library.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="codeconventions.html">Code
        conventions</ulink></para>

        <para>This document describes the programming style I used while
        writing the library. I did not write it to talk you or anyone else
        into using it (although that would be nice.) It could come in handy if
        you're interested in writing your own Components and contributing to
        the project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="memorynote.html">A note on memory
        management</ulink></para>

        <para>This note describes the memory ownership policy used in the
        library, and why this particular ownership policy was chosen.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink type="" url="openglcanvas.html">Creating an OpenGL
        component</ulink></para>

        <para>A step by step tutorial of how to create an OpenGL component
        inside the GUI.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>