<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Book Review: “jQuery UI 1.6: The User Interface Library for jQuery”
  by Dan Wellman</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sidebar>
      <graphic fileref="jquery-ui.png" />

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://www.packtpub.com/user-interface-library-for-jquery/book">jQuery
            UI 1.6: The User Interface Library for jQuery</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Author</term>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://www.packtpub.com/author_view_profile/id/188"
            userlevel="">Dan Wellman</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>ISBN</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>978-1-847195-12-8</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sidebar>

    <para>In the last few months I've been developing a new (work) project and
    decided to give the <ulink type="" url="http://jqueryui.com/">jQuery UI
    library</ulink> a try. I had been using the UI library for a couple of
    weeks before I started reading “<ulink
    url="http://www.packtpub.com/user-interface-library-for-jquery/book">jQuery
    UI 1.6: The User Interface Library for jQuery</ulink>”, and I'm perhaps
    not the typical target audience, so keep that in mind while reading the
    review.</para>

    <para>The first thing that stood out as I started reading were the type
    setting conventions. I usually skip these as they are pretty much the same
    in most books, but somehow in this book they almost take up two pages, in
    what could have been four lines. Odd.</para>

    <para>The book starts with an introduction to the UI library, and goes
    over downloading the library, setting up a environment, themes, the
    different widgets and such. It also explains the structure of the library,
    such as widgets, components and code saving interaction helpers. In my
    opinion it fails to clearly define these terms. Components, widgets and
    interaction helpers are used almost interchangeably. To be fair, this
    seems to be a problem with the jQuery UI library where behaviours such as
    resizing are also grouped under widgets (or components) and not the book.
    In this review I will use the terms component (tabs, dialogs, sliders,
    etc.) and behaviour (resizing, selecting, drag and drop, etc.) from this
    point on to avoid confusion.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Components</title>

    <para>Chapters two trough seven each describe a component: tabs,
    accordion, dialog, slider, date picker, and auto complete<footnote>
        <para>Note that the auto complete component has been removed from the
        jQuery UI library.</para>
      </footnote>. Each chapter explains how to use said component; from basic
    usage it walks the reader through the more advanced options and methods
    and the various styling options. The chapters then conclude with a "Fun
    with …" section, which builds a small sample application demonstrating
    each component. Each component option is explained clearly and usually
    demonstrated in a sample application. Perhaps it is a personal pet peeve,
    but again the examples are very large and take up a lot of unnecessary
    space. I think a lot of these multi-page examples could have been
    simplified by simply showing what has changed with as little context as
    possible. Instead, the book usually reproduces the whole code listing with
    changes highlighted in bold. This includes the parts that are (almost)
    never modified such as the page header and script inclusions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Behaviours</title>

    <para>The next four chapters describe the behaviours in the UI library:
    drag and drop, resizing, selecting, and sorting. These chapters take the
    same approach as the preceding ones: a basic example, styling options,
    overview of all methods and options, and a "Fun with …" section. I
    personally would have put these chapters at the beginning of the book as
    they are used internally in the components and vital to understanding how
    and why the components work. The book then could have progressed by
    building a simple custom component using these behaviours before moving on
    to the built-in components.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>The book concludes with a chapter on the visual effects that come
    with the UI library. I don't have much to say about this chapter, except
    that roughly the same information can be found on the jQuery UI website,
    including live examples of the effects in question. One thing I would have
    liked to see in this book is an overview of the design philosophy and
    choices of the UI library. A small chapter that explains why things are
    done in a certain way would have been a valuable addition to this
    book.</para>

    <para>I think the book's biggest problem is that it covers version 1.6 of
    the jQuery UI library. <ulink url="http://jqueryui.com/">jQuery UI version
    1.7</ulink> has since been released and is different on several points
    (such as <ulink
    url="http://blog.jqueryui.com/2009/03/jquery-ui-17/">theming, available
    options, and methods</ulink>.) Version 1.7 has also removed the auto
    complete component and introduced a new <ulink
    url="http://jqueryui.com/demos/progressbar/">progress bar
    component</ulink> which is not covered in this book. Furthermore, the
    default theme used in the book has been deprecated and is no longer
    available<footnote>
        <para>The jQuery UI team has published an <ulink
        url="http://jqueryui.com/docs/Upgrade_Guide">upgrade guide from 1.6 to
        1.7</ulink>.</para>
      </footnote>. It is not a bad book, but I think it would have been better
    off as either an online tutorial or a wiki so it has a chance to stay up
    to date with the development of jQuery UI. The extensive code examples
    also would have worked better with a website instead of a book.</para>
  </section>
</article>