<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>jLayout — JavaScript Layout Algorithms</title>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Download</title>

    <para>Version 0.3 ― 2008-10-04.</para>

    <para>jLayout Core:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink type="" url="jlayout.js">jlayout.js</ulink>
        (Uncompressed, 8.1KB)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jlayout.min.js">jlayout.min.js</ulink> (Minified,
        4.0KB)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>jQuery plugin:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jquery.jlayout.js">jquery.jlayout.js</ulink>
        (Uncompressed, 3.5KB)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="jquery.jlayout.min.js">jquery.jlayout.min.js</ulink>
        (Minified, 2.3KB)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sidebar>

  <sidebar>
    <title>License</title>

    <para>jLayout is licensed under the <ulink type=""
    url="/licenses/BSD.txt">new BSD license</ulink>. To summarize the license;
    jLayout is completely free for commercial and non-commercial use and you
    can do with it whatever you want, except claim it as your own work.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The jLayout JavaScript library provides layout algorithms for laying
    out components. A component is an abstraction; it can be implemented in
    many ways, for example as items in a HTML5 Canvas drawing or as HTML
    elements. The jLayout library allows you to focus on drawing the
    individual components instead of on how to arrange them on your
    screen.</para>

    <para>The library currently provides three layout algorithms:
    <methodname>border</methodname>, which lays out components in five
    different regions; <methodname>grid</methodname>, which lays out
    components in a user defined grid, and <methodname>flex-grid</methodname>
    which offers a grid with flexible column and row sizes. An <ulink
    url="jquery-plugin.html" userlevel="">experimental jQuery plugin</ulink>
    to lay out (X)HTML elements is also available.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>We start with the definition of a component; a component is
    something that has a minimum size, a preferred size, and a maximum size.
    It also has a method to set its size and position. A container is a
    component that contains other components and lays them out according to a
    layout algorithm (which are provided in the jLayout library.) Components
    need to satisfy the following interface requirements in order to be used
    with the layout algorithms.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>bounds()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the component's position and size as a value object
          with properties <property>x</property>, <property>y</property>,
          <property>width</property> and <property>height</property>. All
          properties should be present in the returned object.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>bounds(value)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the position and size of a component by using a value
          object with properties <property>x</property>,
          <property>y</property>, <property>width</property> and
          <property>height</property>. The individual properties are all
          optional, it is thus legal to supply an empty object, or any
          combination of properties.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>preferredSize()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the component's preferred size (i.e. the size it
          wishes to have) as an object with properties
          <property>width</property> and <property>height</property>. This is
          only a hint, there is no guarantee the component will get the size
          it prefers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>minimumSize()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the component's minimum size (i.e. the size it should
          at least have) as an object with properties
          <property>width</property> and <property>height</property>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>maximumSize()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the component's maximum size (i.e. the size it should
          stay below or equal to) as an object with properties
          <property>width</property> and <property>height</property>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>isVisible()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns <literal>true</literal> if the component is visible
          and should be taken into account when calculating the layout.
          Returns <literal>false</literal> otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>insets()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the offset between a container and its contents as an
          object with properties: <property>top</property>,
          <property>bottom</property>, <property>left</property>, and
          <property>right</property>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>doLayout()</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Calls the <methodname>layout</methodname> method on the layout
          algorithm used to lay out the component (container) it is called on.
          If the component is not a container (and does not have a layout
          algorithm) this method can be left empty.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Note that the distinction between containers and components is
    artificial, both implement the same interface.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Layout Algorithms</title>

    <para>All algorithms are in the <methodname>jLayout</methodname> namespace
    and implement the following interface.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>preferred(container)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the preferred size of the container and its children
          according to the layout algorithm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>minimum(container)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the minimum size the container and its children are
          allowed to have according to the layout algorithm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>maximum(container)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns the maximum size the container and its children are
          allowed to have according to the layout algorithm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>layout(container)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Performs the layout according to the algorithm; resizing and
          positioning children if necessary.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The layout method will not resize the container to accommodate its
    children's preferred size. If a resize is desired, set the bounds of the
    container to its preferred size. The example below shows both ways of
    laying out a container; resizing the children to fit in the container, and
    resizing the container to fit the children.</para>

    <programlisting>// create a layout algorithm
var myLayout = (…)

// lay out without resizing the container
myLayout.layout(container);

// resize the container, then lay it out
container.bounds(myLayout.preferred());
myLayout.layout(container);</programlisting>

    <para>A layout algorithm can be created by calling either the
    <methodname>grid</methodname> or <methodname>border</methodname>
    constructor in the <classname>jLayout</classname> namespace. Both
    constructors take an option object containing layout specific properties.
    Both layouts have the following properties in common:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>hgap</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The horizontal space between the laid out components. Should
          be a number in a coordinate space of your choice. Defaults to 0.
          Optional.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>vgap</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The vertical space between the laid out components. Should be
          a number in a coordinate space of your choice. Defaults to 0.
          Optional.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The other properties are specific to the layout algorithm and are
    discussed below.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Border layout</title>

      <para>The border algorithm lays out components in five different
      regions. These regions are called <property>center</property>,
      <property>north</property>, <property>south</property>,
      <property>east</property> and <property>west</property>. The center
      component will be laid out in the center of the container, north on top
      of it, south beneath it and west and east on the left and right side
      respectively. The layout can only contain one of each region, but all
      are optional. On the right is a visualization of a layout using all five
      regions.</para>

      <graphic fileref="border.png" />

      <para>The border algorithm takes an option object as parameter which can
      contain the following properties:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>center, north, south east, west</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The center, north, south, east or west component. All are
            optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The following example lays out a west, center and north component
      with a vertical space of 5 units between each component. There may be
      additional space between the components and the container if the
      container returns non-zero insets.</para>

      <programlisting>var borderLayout = jLayout.border({
    west:   myWestComponent,
    center: myCenterComponent,
    north:  myNorthComponent,
    vgap: 5
});

borderLayout.layout(myContainer);</programlisting>

      <para>If a region is not specified or the component is not visible its
      space will be taken up by the other components.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Grid layout</title>

      <para>The grid algorithms lays out the components in a grid, and resizes
      each component to the same size. The number of columns and rows can be
      specified by the user. On the right is a visualization of a grid layout
      with four components in a 2x2 grid.</para>

      <graphic fileref="grid.png" />

      <para>The grid algorithm takes an option object as parameter which can
      contain the following properties:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>rows</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of rows in the grid. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>columns</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of columns in the grid. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>items</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An array containing the components to be laid out by the
            algorithm. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The following example lays out four components in a 2x2 grid,
      without any spacing between the components.</para>

      <programlisting>var gridLayout = jLayout.grid({
    rows: 2,
    columns: 2,
    items: [myComponent1, myComponent2, myComponent3, myComponent4]
});

gridLayout.layout(myContainer);</programlisting>

      <para>If the number of rows is given, the number of columns is
      calculated automatically by taking the number of components into
      account. If the number of rows is not given (or set to zero), and the
      number of columns is given, the number of rows will be automatically
      calculated using the number of components. If neither is given, the
      number of rows is set equal to the number of components and the number
      of rows is set to zero.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Flex grid layout</title>

      <para>The flex grid algorithms lays out the components in a grid with
      flexible row and columns sizes. The number of columns and rows can be
      specified by the user. On the right is a visualization of a flex grid
      layout with six components in a 3x2 grid.</para>

      <graphic fileref="flexgrid.png" />

      <para>The flex grid algorithm takes an option object as parameter which
      can contain the following properties:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>rows</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of rows in the flex grid. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>columns</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of columns in the flex grid. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>items</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An array containing the components to be laid out by the
            algorithm. Optional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The following example lays out six components in a 3x2 grid,
      without any spacing between the components.</para>

      <programlisting>var flexGridLayout = jLayout.flexGrid({
    rows: 2,
    columns: 2,
    items: [myComponent1, myComponent2, myComponent3, 
            myComponent4, myComponent5, myComponent6]
});

flexGridLayout.layout(myContainer);</programlisting>

      <para>If the number of rows is given, the number of columns is
      calculated automatically by taking the number of components into
      account. If the number of rows is not given (or set to zero), and the
      number of columns is given, the number of rows will be automatically
      calculated using the number of components. If neither is given, the
      number of rows is set equal to the number of components and the number
      of rows is set to zero.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>